A Guide to the Carr-Cary Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
- Hetty & Jane Margaret Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1825 Aug] 13 (Box Box 2)
  [writes concerning the sickness of Maria Carr, her own abscessed tooth, asks about her business affairs, the Louisiana sugar plantation business, the expected death of Martha's son, and about Francis Gilmer, professor of law]
- Goodwin McBlair to Dabney S. Carr, 1825 Dec 19 (Box Box 2)
  [writes from the ship Peruvian, on his way to Lima, Peru, to tell Dabney goodbye]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Jan 26 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the plantation in Louisiana and other business]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Feb 1 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the sale of sugar from the Louisiana plantation in Baltimore, Mrs. Randolph is in great distress over the death of her daughter, Ann Bankhead, fears that Thomas Jefferson will not get permission to have a lottery because it meets with great opposition, but he will suffer great injury without it, and Jefferson is very unwell]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Feb 8 (Box Box 2)
  [Thomas Jefferson Randolph has gone to Richmond to beseech the General Assembly to allow a lottery for Thomas Jefferson and she discusses her business affairs]
- [L?] Goodwin to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Feb 20 (Box Box 2)
  [is attempting to secure signatures for Dabney's application for a job in the State Department consulate for Columbia but fears that his rival, Mr. Forsyth, has the advantage of prior experience]
- Jane Margaret Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1826] Feb 27 (Box Box 2)
  [disapproves Dabney seeking a consulate position in South America because he and his wife, Sidney, will be so far away, they will soon visit Dunlora, the lottery bill has passed but tickets can only be sold up to the value of the property by disinterested gentlemen and must include Monticello itself, Thomas Jefferson in dreadful spirits, greatly affected by the death of his sister Anne, says Colonel Randolph, "has gone on since his daughter's death more like a demon than ever," the University of Virginia Board of Visitors have chosen no candidate yet, and Frank Gilmer died and was interred at Pen Park]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 3 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the sugar crop's arrival in Baltimore, Dabney's need for a cooper, suggests Spotswood, except Mr. Garret says he can not sell him unless he gets more than he is worth, and Jefferson Randolph is arranging everything for the lottery for Thomas Jefferson]
- Hollins Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 6 (Box Box 2)
  [writes to his brother about his school examinations]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 10 (Box Box 2)
  [her concern over the lottery and raising enough money for Jefferson to keep Monticello, "I cannot bear the idea that the graveyard of almost all my family should be sold if I were to draw it is should never be sold it should be kept for a graveyard for every descendant of the Jefferson race" and the possibility of Dabney Terrell becoming Professor of Law at the University of Virginia]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 13 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the lottery of Thomas Jefferson again, preferring using a subscription to relieve his debt, Jefferson went white when Jefferson Randolph proposed putting Monticello into the lottery, and Uncle Dabney has lost his little boy, Dabney Jefferson Carr (1817-1826)]
- Robert Carter Nicholas to John Spear Smith, 1826 Mar 14 (Box Box 2)
  [the marketing of the sugar from the plantation, prospects of a loan on the plantation, and other related business]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 18 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses plantation affairs, the lottery and subscription to relieve Thomas Jefferson]
- C. J. Carr to Messrs. Dobbin, Murphy, & Bose, 1826 Mar 24 (Box Box 2)
  [forwarding a statement by John Hancocke concerning Thomas Jefferson and his financial woes to be published in their morning paper]
- P. N. Nicholas to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 25 (Box Box 2)
  [fears that to begin subscriptions for the financial relief of Thomas Jefferson in Virginia would injure the chances of success for the lottery]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 29 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the proposal of selling the lottery tickets on Thomas Jefferson's birthday, April 13th and burning them on July 4th when the Vice-President would present the money to him; and Robert wishes her to secure a blacksmith, cooper, and carpenter while she is still in Virginia]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Mar 31 (Box Box 2)
  [repeats the proposal about the lottery described in the previous letter, James Carr is planning on selling his slaves and land, one of whom, Nelson, is a cooper, and the University of Virginia law professor is to be chosen on Monday by the Board of Visitors]
- Lucy Beverly Randolph to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1826 Apr 4 (Box Box 2)
  [contains genealogical notes, the conversion of Burwell Randolph to Catholicism, her mother, the health of [Jane Cary Randolph] improved, they may open a school in Bedford, and family and personal news]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1826?] Apr 4 (Box Box 2)
  [no selection made as yet about the law professorship, but confused by the proposal of William Wirt as professor]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1826?] Apr 11 (Box Box 2)
  [instructions for their return to Baltimore]
- Mrs. Louise McIntire to Jane Margaret Carr, 1826 Jul 6 (Box Box 2)
  [laments the death of Thomas Jefferson, wishing that it had been Colonel Randolph who might have been taken instead but who remains to "torment his family a little longer," her Aunt Maria is to petition the General Assembly for a divorce, and sends greetings from Wilson Cary Newsum (1808-1875) presently at the University of Virginia]
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Jul 11 (Box Box 2)
  [anecdotes of Thomas Jefferson's last days, warns of the attempts of his father, Colonel Thomas Mann Randolph, to get the money raised by selling lottery tickets for Jefferson, and the disposal of Jefferson's estate]
- Clarissa [?] to Jane Margaret Carr, 1826 Sep 17 (Box Box 2)
  [writing from Monticello, describes a concert given by dwarves in Charlottesville, mentions Jane Margaret's suitor, Wilson M. Cary, whom she defends]
- Hollins Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1826 Sep 24 (Box Box 2)
  [writes concerning his examinations]
- M. Nicholas to Dabney S. Carr, [1826] (Box Box 2)
  [concerning the publication of an enclosed circular by Thomas Jefferson found in one of his scrapbooks]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr [?] (Incomplete), [1826?] (Box Box 2)
  [concerning the purchase of slaves]
- Philo Thompson, [1826] (Box Box 2)
  [his statement advocating a subscription to relieve the "Patriot of Monticello" (Thomas Jefferson)]
- Kenderton Smith to Dabney S. Carr, 1827 Jan 31 (Box Box 2)
  [needs the money from Reeder's bonds]
- Susanna Isham Harrison to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1827 Aug 22 (Box Box 2)
  [writes of personal affairs, offering religious encouragement and perspective, heard that John Cocke is at White Sulfur [Springs]
- J. S. Armistead to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1827 Sep 13 (Box Box 2)
  [thanks her for her suggestions about his preaching, and mentions his financial difficulties with his present salary]
- Wilson M. Cary to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Jan 1 (Box Box 2)
  [while studying law with Henry St. George Tucker in Winchester, writes concerning the death of his Uncle Miles, his father's only brother (1789-1827), in Alabama while exploring the Southwest, and warns his mother to keep Archibald constantly in school without interruptions]
- Goodwin McBlair to Dabney S. Carr, 1828 Feb 18 (Box Box 2)
  [reports concerning a meeting of the supporters of his political opponent]
- M[ary] M[unro] Peachy to Virginia Cary, 1828 Apr 26 (Box Box 2)
  [shares social and family news, refers to the death of her daughter, Elizabeth Griffin Peachy Webb, and includes many genealogical notes]
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Dabney S. Carr, 1828 May 3 (Box Box 2)
  [hopes to leave Philadelphia for Baltimore on Monday]
- E. Littell to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Jun 10 (Box Box 2)
  [refers to the papers forwarded by her for the editor of
  Remember Me
  ]
- Samuel Hurd to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Jun 18 (Box Box 2)
  [writing from the Union Theological Seminary, refers to her literary labors, and the progress of revival services]
- Thomas Mann Randolph to Dabney S. Carr, 1828 Jul 13 (Box Box 2)
  [asks for assistance in securing a steam boat between Norfolk and Baltimore]
- Samuel J. Hollins to Dabney S. Carr, 1828 Jul 13 (Box Box 2)
  [Wilson died at the plantation in Louisiana]
- Susan A. Pool to Virginia Cary, 1828 Jul 18 (Box Box 2)
  [mentions the upcoming marriage of Virginia's daughter, Mary Randolph Cary (1811-1887) and Dr. Orlando Fairfax (1806-1882) and religious matters]
- Robert Carter Nicholas to J. S. Smith, 1828 Jul 19 (Box Box 2)
  [the death of Wilson at the plantation in Louisiana]
- William Meade to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Aug 28 (Box Box 2)
  [writes concerning Mrs. Flournoy?]
- Samuel Hurd to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Sep 16 (Box Box 2)
  [the nature of his examinations at Union Theological Seminary and religious matters]
- M[ary] M[unro] Peachy to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1828 Sep 24 (Box Box 2)
  [writes concerning the death of William Newsum (1785-1828), the estate of Miles Cary of "Oak Hill," and other news of family and friends]
- Dabney S. Carr to John H. Eaton, 1829 Feb 24 (Box Box 2)
  [the cost of the publication of the Baltimore
  Republican
- S. [?] Goodwin to Dabney S. Carr, 1829 Mar 12 (Box Box 2)
  [inquires as to the status of his possible appointment under Andrew Jackson's administration]
- S. [?] Goodwin to Dabney S. Carr, 1829 Mar 15 (Box Box 2)
  [discusses the status of his possible appointment under Andrew Jackson's administration]
- Samuel Hurd to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1829 Jul 1 (Box Box 2)
  [reports concerning Andover Theological Seminary]
- Susan A. Pool to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1829 Sep 18 (Box Box 2)
  [family and personal news]
- Harriet Randolph Hackley to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1829 Nov 16 (Box Box 2)
  [the birthday of Martha Jefferson Hackley (1824-?)]
- Martha Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, [182-?] (Box Box 2)
  [asks Jefferson to let Thrimston remain to help Gorman repair the portico which has been ripped up, revealing the red dirt underneath, or they will all be mired in the dining room]
- Martha Randolph to Peter Carr, [182-?] Aug 23 (Box Box 2)
  [if possible Ann will wait for Mr. Nicholas tomorrow, but after that the Madisons will be with them]
- Dabney Carr to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Feb 9 (Box Box 3)
  [legal advice to appeal to a judicial tribunal to decide upon and assign to Virginia her rights, and call the person in question (the administrator?) to account; and to secure a copy of the will]
- Dabney Carr to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Mar 1 (Box Box 3)
  [discusses Virginia's prospective school and encloses the receipt from John Gordon]
- Elizabeth Ball to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Aug 5 (Box Box 3)
  [sends a box of Bibles from the Bible Society of Virginia to be distributed in Fluvanna County]
- Mary B. Randolph & [?] to Sidney (Mrs. Dabney S.) Carr, 1830 Sep 10 (Box Box 3)
  [family news, the birth of twin boys to Ellen Coolidge, and plans to use the garret for a school room]
- Sally Newsum to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Sep 14 (Box Box 3)
  [her beloved Cary has been at the point of death for 20 days, has gotten a letter from Lucius Cary, Aunt Hetty Carr and Wilson Cary, when he and Jane Margaret Carr are married, will live in Mr. Davis's new house, and mentions the financial ruin of the Buchannons]
- E. W. Hudnall to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Nov 4 (Box Box 3)
  [discusses the sale and distribution of Bibles in Fluvanna County]
- Susan A. Pool to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1830 Dec 20 (Box Box 3)
  [the marriages of Virginia's son, Wilson Miles Cary to Jane Margaret Carr (1809-1903), and daughter, Jane Blair (1808-1888) to the Rev. Edward Dunlap Smith, of New York, and the serious illness of Mrs. Betsy Carr]
- Martha Jefferson Minor to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1831 Nov 28 (Box Box 3)
  [includes genealogical notes, describes her school, financial terms, and her teacher, welcomes the addition of scholar Virginia Pasture, and her sympathy for motherless children]
- Peggy Nicholas to her daughter, Sidney (Mrs. Dabney S.) Carr (1805- 1886), 1832 Feb 27 (Box Box 3)
  [grateful that her son, John, survived an attack of cholera on his ship, fears that Jefferson Randolph's decision to run for office will bring about financial ruin, Jane has received a check from the Proctor at the University of Virginia, asks about the folks at Montebello and John Smith, mentions people at Monticello, and the birth of boys to both Virginia Trist and Jane Smith]
- Jane Margaret Cary to Sidney (Mrs. Dabney S.) Carr, 1834 Jan 7 (Box Box 3)
  [describes her voyage from Baltimore to St. Augustine on the General Marion, the storm off Cape Hatteras, the rough seas on the way to Charleston drove them past he port to Sullivan's Island and they had to sail back, upon their arrival the mists were too thick to attempt to enter the port of Charleston, another ship collided with her vessel while at anchor and damaged it, though it did not sink, they took a little schooner Samuel Mills the rest of the way, encountering a strong gale near Florida, and her thankfulness that little Sally was safe at home with Sidney]
- Jane Margaret Cary to Sidney (Mrs. Dabney S.) Carr, [1834] Mar 17 (Box Box 3)
  [reports on the improvements in her health, the many others in Florida who do not appear able to recover, and the purchase of Indian ponies by Wilson]
- Jane Margaret Cary to Sarah E. Nicholas, 1834 Apr 9 (Box Box 3)
  [discusses the improvements in her health, religion, her separation from her little girl, and their projected trip back home from Florida]
- Wilson M. Cary to Dabney S. Carr, 1834 Apr 27 (Box Box 3)
  [plans to leave Florida on the schooner S.S. Mills next week, praises the climate of Florida but not its civilization, discusses the health of Jane Margaret, and their plan "to try the leeches" for her throat in Charleston, and mentions the financial panic, where even the office holders in Florida are cursing President Jackson]
- S.[?] Goodwin to Dabney S. Carr, 1839 Apr 1 (Box Box 3)
  [has had a conversation with Mr. Barney who promises that nothing further on an unnamed subject would be published in
  The Patriot
- James Broadhead to Dabney S. Carr, 1839 May 6 (Box Box 3)
  [writes from St. Charles County, Missouri, studying law with Mr. Bates, his father's farm doing well, especially with his tobacco crop, his sickness, and all the agues promoted by the number of swamps and ponds nearby, most of the immigrants are from Virginia, Tennessee, and Kentucky, and the beautiful spring season in Missouri]
- Dabney Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] Jan 19 (Box Box 3)
  [the hire of slave Peter]
- John Hollins Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] Apr 14 (Box Box 3)
  [writes of events at home to his older brother, his schooling, and the whipping of the slave Peter]
- Sidney (Mrs. Dabney S.) Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] Apr 25 (Box Box 3)
  [their son's health has improved but his behavior has worsened since his father has been in Washington]
- Jane M. H. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] May 4 (Box Box 3)
  [writes to her brother, Ellen has gone to Richmond with cousin Betsy and cousin James to have her teeth filled, the fruit in the neighborhood is killed and the Blue Ridge Mountains filled with snow]
- John Hollins Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] May 4 (Box Box 3)
  [William Patterson has gone away, and paid for a hatchet before he could get it]
- Hetty Carr to George Pitt Stevenson, [18--?] Oct 24 (Box Box 3)
  [plans to leave Dabney with Mr. Hollins if possible, her sympathy for Eliza because she will not accompany George [to Cuba?]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 18[?] Nov 1 (Box Box 3)
  [discusses the sale of her slaves, which would bring more in a public sale but she prefers to sell privately to those she knows, and other business affairs]
- Louisa Cocke to Mrs. Virginia Cary, [18--?] (Box Box 3)
  [asks to borrow a glass lamp because one of hers is broken]
- Louisa Cocke to Mrs. Virginia Cary, [18--?] (Box Box 3)
  [expects her husband back from Charlottesville soon, and misses her child Nanny]
- Dabney S. Carr to Aunt Margaret Spear Smith (1759-1842) (Box Box 3)
  [draft of a letter which urges her to make a will]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [18--?] (Box Box 3)
  [warns him against bad influences, laments the loss of Maria [Jefferson Carr (1804-1825)?], and regrets his financial reverses]
- Hetty Carr to [?], [18--?] (Box Box 3)
  [writes concerning the debts of her nephew, George N. O[verton?]
- Back of letter to Mrs. Carr, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Financial Documents, 1786-1830 (Box Box 3)
- Debate Manuscripts by Peter Carr at [William and Mary ?], [ca. 1785] (Box Box 3)
- Mrs. Virginia Cary - Poems, 1827 Jul 9 (Box Box 3)
- Mrs. Virginia Cary - Poem, "Moonlight", 1829 Jun 15 (Box Box 3)
- Satirical Poem re: John Marshall Decision (of 1821?) (Box Box 3)
- Manuscript Poem, n. d. (Box Box 3)
- Obituary of Peter Carr by William Wirt, 1815 Feb 17 (Box Box 3)
- Obituary for Colonel Robert Jouett, 18[--?] June 4 (Box Box 3)